# Diego Alburez-Gutierrez

Konrad-Zuse-Straße 1, 18057 Rostock, Germany alburezgutierrez@demogr.mpg.de; www.alburez.me

I am a social scientist specialising in inter-generational demography. My work has used mathematical modeling, micro-simulation techniques, and empirical analysis to explore changes in the experience of life events such as kin availability, family bereavement, and caring responsibilities across demographic regimes.

## **EDUCATION**

#### The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

PhD, Demography and Population Studies

2014 - 2018

- Summary: Effects of mass violence and genocide on population dynamics.
- Data collection: Genealogical surveys and in-depth interviews (1 year fieldwork)
- Mixed methods research design:
  - Quantitative analysis: Descriptive demographic, regression and survival models, network analysis
  - Qualitative analysis: Thematic and framework analysis
- Supervisors: Arjan Gjonça, Tiziana Leone, Ernestina Coast, and Michael Murphy

MSc, Social Research Methods (Distinction)

2013-2014

Practical approach with emphasis on quantitative and qualitative data analysis

# Del Valle University, Guatemala

context of global population aging.

BA, Anthropology (First class)

2008-2012

Thesis on evaluation methodologies for Conditional Cash Transfer Programmes

#### AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- 2019 Otto Hahn Medal (2020) awarded by the Max Planck Society for 'outstanding achievement from the initial creative period of young scientists', in particular 'for methodological innovations for studying the long-term consequences of mass killings on local populations'
- LSE PhD Academy Prize (2018) awarded by the London School of Economics for research on statesponsored massacres in Guatemala
- LSE PhD Studentship (2014-2018) awarded by the London School of Economics

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany

Research Scientist (post-doc) and Research Area Chair (Aging and Generational Processes), Lab of Digital and Computational Demography

Since 2018
Leading role in projects using innovative data and approaches to understand demographic change in the

United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Denmark

Statistics Team Intern, Field Information and Coordination Support Section (FICSS) Central role in implementing UNHCR's Demographic Projection Tool.

2018

| The London | School | of Economics | and Political | Science, | $\mathbf{U}\mathbf{K}$ |
|------------|--------|--------------|---------------|----------|------------------------|
|------------|--------|--------------|---------------|----------|------------------------|

Research Assistant, Law Department Leading qualitative research on low student satisfaction 2017

Research Assistant, Social Policy Department

Quantitative analysis of maternal and child health outcomes in Palestine

Research Assistant, Sociology Department

2014-2015

2016-2017

Qualitative coding and analysis of methodological practices in sociology of work

Research Assistant, Methodology Department

2013-2014

Survey of grey literature to identify common qualitative methods in International Development

# Public Opinion Program, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala

Lead researcher

2013

Designing and implementing qualitative research for the Media Monitoring Project

#### The Population Council, Guatemala

Research Sub Coordinator

2012

- Design and implementation of qualitative research on conditional cash transfer programmes
- Led team of four ethnographers during six months of data collection in rural Guatemala

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## European Doctoral School of Demography (EDSD), Barcelona

Class Teacher for course "Digital Demography"

2020-2021

## The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

Class Teacher, Social Policy Department

2016-2017

- Leading seminars for the course "Introduction to Global Population Change"
- Weekly office hours, updated course website, homework and exam marking

Class Teacher, LSE Methods Summer School

2015

- Leading seminars for the "Qualitative Research Methods" strand
- Homework and exam marking

# Del Valle University, Guatemala

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department

2013

- Leading seminars for the course "Advanced qualitative data analysis"
- Course design, wrote NVivo course pack (Spanish), homework and exam marking

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department

Leading seminars for the course "History of Anthropology 1"

2011

#### PUBLICATIONS IN PEER-REVIEWED JOURNALS

**Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Kolk, M., and Zagheni, E. (Forthcoming) "Women's experience of child death: A global demographic perspective." Demography. Temporary doi: 10.31235/osf.io/s69fz.

Smith-Greenaway, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Trinitapoli, J, and Zagheni, E. (2021) "The Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: Indicators of the Cumulative Prevalence of Child Loss." BMJ Global Health,

- 6:e004837. doi:bmjgh-2020-004837
- Basellini, U., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Del Fava, E., Perrotta, D., Bonetti, M., Camarda, C. and Zagheni, E. (Forthcoming). "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic in England and Wales." SSM Population Health. Temporary doi: 10.31235/osf.io/75d6m.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Mason, C., and Zagheni, E. (Forthcoming). "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." Population and Development Review (Conditional acceptance). Temporary doi: 10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2020-037.
- Nepomuceno, M., Acosta, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Aburto, J.M., Gagnon, A., and Turra, C. (2020). "Besides population age-structure, health and other demographic factors can contribute to understanding the COVID-19 burden." Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 117(25). doi:10.1073/pnas.2008760117.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (2019). Blood is thicker than bloodshed: A genealogical approach to reconstruct populations after armed conflicts. Demographic Research, 40(23): 627-656. doi:10.4054/DemRes.2019.40.23.
- Leone, T., Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Gandour, R., Coast, E., and Giacaman, R. (2019). "Maternal and child access to care and intensity of conflict in the occupied Palestinian territory: a pseudo-longitudinal analysis (2000–2014)." Conflict and Health 13(36). doi:10.1186/s13031-019-0220-2.
- Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Chandrasekharan, E., Chunara, R., Gil-Clavel, S., Hannak, A., Interdonato, R., Joseph, K., Kalimeri, K., Malik, M., Mayer, K., Mejova, Y., Paolotti, D., and Zagheni, E. (2019). "Reports of the Workshops Held at the 2019 International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media." AI Magazine, 40(4), 78-82. doi:10.1609/aimag.v40i4.5287.
- McGovern, P., and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez**. (2017) "Who takes workplace case-study methods seriously? The influence of gender, academic rank and PhD training." Industrial Relations Journal 48(2):98-114, doi:10.1111/irj.12171.

# **BOOK CHAPTERS**

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, S. Aref, S. Gil-Clavel, A. Grow, D.V. Negraia, E. Zagheni. (2019). "Demography in the Digital Era: New Data Sources for Population Research." Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the Italian Statistical Society. doi: 10.31235/osf.io/24jp7.

## TECHNICAL REPORTS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** and Segura Garcia, C. (2018). "The UNHCR Demographic Projection Tool: estimating the future size and composition of forcibly displaced populations." UNHCR Statistics Technical Series: 2018/1. Copenhagen: United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.

# WORKING PAPERS AND PAPERS IN PROGRESS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (2021). "The demographic drivers of grief and memory after genocide in Guatemala." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-003.

- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "Mortality change and its impact on child survival." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-001.
- Riffe, T., Acosta, E., Aburto, J. M., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, et al. (2020) "COVerAGE-DB: a database of age-structured COVID-19 cases and deaths." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi: 10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2020-032.
- Martinez-Folgar, K., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Paniagua-Avila, A., Ramirez-Zea, M., Bilal, U. (in progress). "Excess Mortality During the COVID-19 Pandemic in Guatemala".

#### SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "DemoKin: An R package to implement matrix kinship models in stable and non-stable populations". https://github.com/IvanWilli/DemoKin.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**. and Iemmi, Valentina. (2019). "'suffrager': a feminist colour palette for R." https://github.com/alburezg/suffrager

# INVITED PRESENTATIONS (SELECTED)

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (16 April 2021, online due to Covid-19) "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic." El Colegio de Mexico, Mexico.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (08 Dec 2020, online due to Covid-19) "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." Population and Health Research Group Seminar Series, St Andrews, Scotland (University of St Andrews).
- Alburez-Gutierrez, D. (27 May 2020, postponed due to Covid-19 lockdown) "Die demografischen Auswirkungen von Massengewalt in Guatemala [The demographic consequences of Genocide in Guatemala]." Berlin, Germany (Ibero-American Institute).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (27 Nov 2019) "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective." ISER External Seminar, Colchester, UK (Institute for Social and Economic Research, University of Essex).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (23 May 2019) "The Demographic Foundations of the Lived Experience of Kin Death: A Genealogical Reconstruction." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (25 April 2019) "Ciencias Sociales Computacionales: Retos y oportunidades en la era digital [Computational Social Sciences: challenges and opportunities in the Digital Age]". Guatemala City, Guatemala (Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences).
- Alburez-Gutierrez, D. (8 February 2018) "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University).

#### OUTREACH AND SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

 Academic video: 'How Can We Quantify the Immediate and Lingering Impact of Genocide on Local Populations?' (Latest Thinking, Apr 2020)

- Opinion piece: 'Coronavirus: a warning to Latin America and the Caribbean to dramatically increase COVID-19 testing' (The Conversation, UK, Apr 2020)
- Blog post: 'Genocide is the tip of the iceberg: Reviewing the Guatemalan case' (LSE Human Rights Blog, Feb 2016)

#### **SKILLS**

- Statistical programming: R (base, tidyverse, data.table, parallel, shiny), Stata, Excel
- Text processing and web: LATEX, MS Office, (r)markdown, HTML, JavaScript, Tesseract
- Other programming: Git, Python 3, SQL, Hadoop
- Demographic microsimulation: SOCSIM with applications in R
- Qualitative data analysis: NVivo, Atlas.ti
- Experience in qualitative, quantitative, and online data collection

#### LANGUAGES

- International: **Spanish** (native), **English** (full professional C2), **German** (full professional C1), **Swedish** (beginner A1)
- Guatemalan/Mexican: **K'iche'** (full professional C1), **Achi** (full professional C1), **Kaqchikel** (professional B1), **Q'eqchi'** (limited working A2)

## ORGANISER OF INTERNATIONAL ACADEMIC EVENTS

- Coordinator of the Seminar Series of the Lab of Digital and Computational Demography, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research.
- Organiser and moderator: Panel Discussion on Digital and Computational Demography, IX Conference of the Latin American Association for Population Studies, Santiago, Chile (online)
- Organiser: Rostock Open Science Workshop, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Rostock
- Organiser: Workshop on Demographic Research with Web and Social Media Data, 13<sup>th</sup> International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), Munich

## SERVICE TO THE DISCIPLINE

- Reviewer for academic journals: Demography; Population and Development Review; Population Studies; Journal of Marriage and Family; PLOS ONE; Demographic Research; Revue Quetelet/Quetelet Journal; EPJ Data Science; 11<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Social Informatics (SocInfo '19)
- Organiser of the 'Social Policy Qualitative Research Group', London School of Economics 2017-2018
- President of the 'Methodology Student Union', London School of Economics 2013-2014
- President of the 'Social Sciences Student Union', Del Valle University (Guatemala) 2011-2012

## PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP)
- British Society for Population Studies (BSPS)
- Population Association of America (PAA)
- European Association for Population Studies (EAPS)
- Latin American Association for Population Studies (ALAP)
- Latin American Studies Association (LASA)
- Households in Conflict Network (HiCN)
- International Science, Technology, and Innovation Network of Guatemala (REDCTI)